欢迎收看 我是马克
Reporters on France24. I am Mark Owen.
本期节目我们关注中国异议人士失踪之谜
In this edition the mystries of why those who expressed views different to those of the government disappeared in China
听多了关于中国经济 环境 文化扩张的报道
We spent a lot of time as journalist reporting on the business environment and culture reach of China
本期节目将揭示和北京有不同意见的人士所面对的恐怖
This program though will expose the horror of being a person who dares to disagree with Beijing
其在生理 心理 及经济上的残忍程度是我们很多人无法想象的
You'll see it's of a cruelty many of us will find impossible to imagine physically psychologically financially too
人权卫士也可能包括马克龙总统
Defenders of human rights politically speaking of being that including the French president Emmanuel Macron
交易完成了 异议人士的命运却还是个未知数
Deals are done dissidents though and everyone else whose views and conduct may not be in step with the government suffer an unknown fate
原则在利益面前往往落败
When it comes to trade vs principles trade always wins
还有那些失踪者的家人们...
What about the families of those who were still missing
让我们一起来看看两位记者Forget和Vedeilhe的报道
as reports by Angelique Forget and Antoine Vedeilhe
一位书商的遭遇震动了香港
关押 审讯数月
他被中国政府绑架
仅仅因为店里出售批评北京方面的书籍
书商失踪8个月后回家
... bookseller to return home after been missing for eight months
本周早些时候（2016年6月14日） 林荣基
Earlier this week Lam Wing Kee
成为五名被绑架书商中第四位重返香港的人
became the fourth of five booksellers to resurface in Hong Kong
他的故事传遍全球
His story spread around the world
2015年10月（解说误为2016）林荣基
In October 2015 Lam Wing Kee
铜锣湾书店店长 在深圳失踪
a book seller in Hong Kong disappeared in the South of China
他的家人8个月没有他的任何消息
For eight months his relatives had no news of him
恢复自由后 他开了一个记者会
Upon his release he gave a press conference
讲述了他被中国政府绑架和拘押的经历
where he said he was kidnapped and detained by Chinese authorities
我非常害怕
I was really scared
我不知道在哪里 也没有人可以求助
I was lost I felt lonely with no one to help me
我不知道他们要干什么
I didn't know what they do to me
他们做的是非法的
What they did was not legal
我不知道他们是否会正式起诉我
I wondered if they would have put me on trial
失踪事件过去两年 林荣基仍无法释怀
Two years after his disappearance Lam Wing Kee still can't turn the page
书店已被当局下令停业
The bookstore in which he worked was closed by order of the authortities
这是我的书店
Here is my bookstore
当我到附近
When I come in to the neigborhood
就过来看一下
I came here to take a look
最近贴了一张通知
Someone recently put a note
上面写着暂停营业
There it says hold on
一些老客户非常喜欢我们的书店
Some customers were really grateful for the work that was done in this bookstore
林荣基不是个案
Lam Wing Kee isn't the only one who went missing
人权律师王宇失踪了18个月
Wang Yu a human rights lawyer went missing for eighteen month
瑞典一个非政府组织负责人彼得·达林失踪了23天
Peter Dahlin the Swedish head of an NGO wasn't seen for 23 days
李文足仍在寻找她失踪的丈夫
Li Wenzu is still looking for her husband
类似还有几百人被绑架 完全失去和外面世界的联系
Like them hundreds of others have been kidnapped and hidden away from the outside world
他们经受到了什么
What happens when these people vanish
他们被关在哪里
Where are they detained
为何人权卫士们受到如此密集的打击
Why are the targets so often defenders of human rights
我们采访了几位被失踪的当事人
We track down some of China's disappeared
王宇是中国知名的人权律师
Wang Yu is one of China's most famous human rights lawyers
也是首批被失踪的人
and was among the first to disappear
顶着自身和家人安全的压力 她秘密接受了我们的采访
She agrees to meet us in secret dispite threats to her and her family
2015年七月九日深夜 她在家中被国安人员带走
On July 9th 2015 in the middle of the night she was arrested at home by the state security services
冲进来很多人 几十个
There were a lot of them several dozen
他们把我按在床上 把这个手反背过来
They throw me on the bed put my hands behind my back
很多人压过来 然后压过来以后
There were a lot of them against me
就把我拷上手铐
They handcuffed me and held me tight
戴上黑头套
Then they put a bag over my head
然后就给我往门外拖
and they took me out of my home
王宇被控颠覆国家政权
Wang Yu was accused of subverting state power
被关押 被酷刑
For more than a year she was detained and tortured
很长时间不让吃饭 不让喝水
They deprived me of food and water sleep too
然后五天五夜不让睡觉
They prevented me from sleeping for five days and five nights
我感觉他们的目的是把我虐待死一样
I felt they wanted to torture me until I died
我不知道当时是怎么过过来的
I still wonder how I made it to the end
好像是死了一次了
In fact I felt as though I died there
从王宇突然失踪那晚起 当局开始全面打压异议人士
The sudden disappearance of Wang Yu marked the beginning of a wave of arrest in China
涉及了将近300名律师和人权捍卫者
In total nearly three hundred laywers and human rights defenders disappeared from one day to the next
很多人被判有期徒刑
Some have since been sentenced to long jail terms
因为打压从2015年7月9日开始 被称为709事件
The purge which started on the 9th of July 2015 has become known as the 709 inccident
在北京我们有幸走访到一位还在为被打压同行进行辩护的律师
In Beijing we met one of the only lawyers to defend his colleges who's been imprisoned or threated by the Chinese authorities
他的办公室有几十个这样的案卷
In his office he has dozens of files
梁小军(人权律师) 很多涉案人员及家属和我签了委托书 这样我可以代理他们
There are many relatives of the members of the 709 inccident who have filed their cases with us so that I can represent them
有很多 很多委托书
I can show you their letters there are many
比如这些人的 像这个是李玉凤的
For example here there is a letter from Li Yufeng
涉嫌寻讯滋事
She was accused of disturbing public order
已经被抓了
she was arrested
这是江天勇的委托书 当时江天勇害怕自己被抓
This is a letter from Jiang Tianyong he was afraid of being arrested
梁小军知道接这些敏感案件 他也可能被失踪
Liang Xiaojun knows that by taking these cases he could also disappear
我也害怕也有恐惧
I am scared too of course I am scared
我觉得作为人权案件的代理律师 很多人都生活在恐惧之中
I think that many human rights lawyers live in fear
2012年生效的一条法律允许当局带走嫌疑犯
Since 2012 a Chinese law allows authorities to remove suspects and hold them in secret
并秘密关押长达6个月的时间
This detention can last six months
这样的法律条文 梁小军更愿意称其为黑监狱
A legal framework for what Liang Xiaojun prefers to call Black Jails
在中国它不叫黑监狱 叫指定居所监视居住
In China the Black Jails we call them Residential Surveillance at a Disignated Place
他说这个地方是我指定的地方
Can be anywhere
对你进行监视居住 实际上就是失踪
In fact that says these people has been disappeared
具体在哪里我们并不知道
It's not clear where these places are
出来的人他们也不能具体指明在哪里
Even the people who come out can't say where they were
他们被带到那个地方以后 进一个小黑屋 见不到阳光 然后里面有人进行24小时看守
Inside these people are placed in a room where guards monitor them 24x7
全程记录
And everything they do was recorded
限制身体活动
Their movements are limited
对他们进行殴打 甚至酷刑
They are beaten tortured
对他们询问
They must answer questions
甚至进行心理折磨
They are tortured physically and psychologically
这种地方你说不是监狱 但实际上它就是黑监狱
These places aren't called Black Jails but in fact they are Black Jails
这些失踪行为是由中国政府协调操控的
These disappearances are orchestrated by the Chinese government
在习近平掌握最高权力以后 开始了对公民社会和不同意见的全面打压
Since taking office Xi Jinping has been cracking down on civil society and surpressing all dissenting voices
坚决反对一切削弱 歪曲 否定党的领导和我国社会主义制度的言行
We must firmly fight the words and actions that undermine and disrupt the authority of the parties
这是一个对希望拥有更多自由的人的警告
A warning for anyone who wants more freedom
对国际人权组织来说 这次打压让人联想起中国历史的几次黑暗时期
For human rights groups this repression is reminicent of dark times in Chinese history
大赦国际中国研究员威廉： 1978年以来中国调整路线开始改革开放 尽力融入国际社会
Since reform and opening in 1978 when China took a historic change of course to try to reintegrate with the world and with global institutions
这次打压可以说是自89天安门事件以来最严重的一次
Its been one of the worst crackdowns since arguably since the Tiananmen Square crackdown in 1989
在中国 有一位律师成为北京政府威权倾向的代表性人物
In China one lawyer has become the symbol of Beijing's authoritarian tendencies
王全璋是数百名失踪人员中唯一一位至今没有任何下落的人
Wang Quanzhuang is the last of the hundreds missing people never to have resurfaced
李文足（王全璋妻子） 这是15年5月我们一起的相片
This photo was taken in May 2015
就隔了两个月 他就被抓了
Two months later he was arrested
所以这张相片基本上记住了我们最后在一起相处的时间吧
This is one of the last beautiful moments we have together
他2年半前失踪以后
Since his disappearance two and a half years ago
他妻子和现在已经5岁的儿子再也没有得到过他的消息
his wife and their 5 year old son haven't heard from him
想爸爸
I miss my dad
贴到这儿吧
Here I put this picture
爸爸快回来 爸爸快回来
There it says Dad come back quickly Dad come back quickly
王全璋被带走后有一直被秘密关押
Since his arrest Wang Quanzhuang has been held in secret
没人知道他的下落
Nobody knows where he is
律师 我聘请的律师从来没有被会见过
The lawyers I hired to defend him don't have the right to visit him
包括这个通讯我们没有
And I don't have the right to communiate with him
我们没有他的一点点消息
We don't have any news
不知道在里面是怎么样
I don't know how he is doing
我不知道他这个人是不是还 我没办法去想 不知道
in fact I don't even know if he is still alive but I don't allow myself to think about that because it's too painful to imagine
没有他任何消息
I don't know anything
就这样被中国政府 就是这样
I have no news
把一个人就这样 一个好人 就因为说了真话 是律师 平白无故消失了
My husband was such a beautiful person and honest man
890多天了 两年半 没有他任何消息
Because of the Chinese government its been 890 days two and half years now that I have no news
我们对中国政府方面提出了有关王全璋下落的采访要求 但没有收到答复
The Chinese authorities didn't respond to our request for interviews regarding Wang Quanzhuang's fate
在中国 捍卫自由会导致流亡
In China defending freedom can lead to exile
邻国泰国成了流亡人士的避难港
A neighboring country has become a refuge for those fleeing repression
这里是几百名流亡中国公民的藏身地
We traval to Tailand where hundreds of Chinese nationals are hiding out
也是瑞典活动家彼得用于避难的新家
It's also home now to a Swedish activist who sought refuge
彼得·达林曾是北京一个帮助中国人权捍卫者组织的负责人
Peter Dahlin used to head up an NGO in Beijing helping human rights defenders
当局在2016年1月将他逮捕 指控他颠覆政权
For this the Chinese government accused him of subversion and arrested him in January 2016
在一本由十多位被失踪者在海外出版的新书中 他也讲述了他的故事
He's told the story of his disapperance and detention in a book written with other victims
有十一个律师 媒体人 非政府组织员工参与了这本书
We got eleven people lawyers some media workers NGO workers
他们都被指定居所监视居住
All were placed in RSDP -- the Black Jails of Chinese power
彼得好几天不让睡觉
Peter Dahlin was deprived of sleep for several days
在这里你被隔离
Because in here you are alone there is nothing
没有检察官来看你
There is no prosecuter that will come to shake on you
没有律师会见
There is no right to access a lawyer
家人不知道你的关押地点
Your family will not be notified where you are
不需要任何司法程序他们可以关你6个月
And they can keep you for six months without any judicial process
你没有上诉的权力
You have no right to any appeal
彼得被关押23天
Peter Dahlin remained locked up for 23 days
为了得到自由 他被迫在电视上公开认罪
To get out he was forced to confess his crimes on a Chinese public television
我的行为违反了中国的法律
I violated the Chinese law through my activities here
我伤害了中国政府
and I have caused harm to the Chinese government
我也伤害了中国人民的感情
and I have hurt the feelings of the Chinese people
我真诚地道歉
I apologize sincerely for this
对于这些我感到非常抱歉
and I am very sorry for what happened
所有的内容都事先安排好
Everything that has been said was written down before
问什么如何回答都有严格审查好的书面文稿
The questions and the answers were written down studied adjusted
其实就是我和央视的记者
And it was basically me and this journalist from CCTV
都有我们的稿子 她有稿子 我也有 她读她的 我读我的
who would simply read our lines she had the paper I had the paper she would read the question I would read the answer
近年来中国加大了强迫认罪的使用
In recent years China has increased the use of forced confessions
强迫认罪被作为证据用于庭审 这也可以减弱人权捍卫者的威望
They are used as evidence during trials and undermines the power of human rights defenders
大赦国际中国研究员威廉： 当你看到你熟识的人权捍卫者
When you look at someone that you've respected and you know that they are fighters for human rights
在说一些你绝对想不到他们会说的话的时候
Then you see them reading a statement and saying something that you will never believe that they would say before
这会让人们害怕
I mean that stikes fear inside people
难以想象政府做了什么才会使他们说那样的话
because they only can imagine what the government did in order to get that person to say those type of things
为了避免这样的情况 杨伯军（音）在两年前决定离开北京
To avoid such a scenario Yang Bojun decided to leave Beijing two years ago
我们在曼谷的街头见到了他
We catch up with him in the streets of Bangkok
他在中国是大学的经济学老师 同时推动中国民主化
In China he taught economics at university and was active in the prodemocracy movement
中国的政府大力抓捕我们这种不同政见者
The Chinese communist party wants to arrent people like me who have different political opinions
为了不坐牢不受迫害我别无选择
To avoid prison and to void being prosecuted I have no other choice
没有办法才逃到这里来生活
I can only run away and live here
在曼谷也比较危险
Even here in Bangkok there are always risks
为了避免麻烦我常常会看看有没有人跟踪我 出来的时候
To avoid to put myself in danger I often look behind me to make sure I am not being followed
即使离开中国 杨伯军（音）也没有安全感
Even outside of China Yang Bojun doesn't feel safe
北京政府常常跨出国门抓捕异见者
Beijing doesn't let borders limits its persuit of dissidents
现在他远离家人藏到一个诊所里
Today he is forced to hide far from his family in the premises of a medical office
这是我起居的地方
Here is where I live
我在里面生活 睡觉 做饭
This is where I sleep I cook everything happens here
这是洗衣机 就在这个地方
It's also here that I run my machines
我以前是在北京买了一个二居室
Before I owned my apartment in China a two bed room apartment with a living room too
和爱人孩子我们三个人住在一起
I lived here with my wife and child
在泰国杨伯军（音）取得了联合国难民身份
In Tailand Yang Bojun has been granted refugee status by the United Nations
就觉得很不可思议 自己从来没想到会流亡泰国
To me this is an incredible situation because in China I would never have imagined that one day I would be exiled in Tailand
成为难民
and that I would become a refugee
不过是想为这个国家 为了让人民生活得好点
All that I did was to improve my country and to serve the people
没想到自己因此流亡海外
I didn't think it would lead to me being in exile
逃到国外 用古人的话来说
I would have to flee and live abroad
变成鬼了 做梦也没有想到这个事情是这样一个情况
I didn't think I would be like a ghost for my country even in my worst nightmares I wouldn't think I would get here
家人 朋友 祖国 杨伯军（音）都失去了
His family his friends his country for Yang Bojun the Chinese government has taken them all
泰国也只是第一站
And Tailand is only an initial step
他希望能在美国重建自己的人生
He hopes to rebuild his life in the United States
希望能顺利离开 而不是被失踪
escaping again rather than disappearing
本台记者Forget和Vedeilhe
By Angelique Forget and Antoine Vedeilhe
我们的网址是France24.com 这里是Reporters
See it again at our website Frace24.com. This is Reporters on France24
请不要离开
Stay with us
每日油兔字幕组 @wanggonging 2018.2.11